Finding Aid for Edward William Staebler papers, 1870-1952
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward William Staebler papers 1870-1952, 1922-1944
Staebler, Edward William, 1872-1946.
4 linear feet
8643 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan businessman and Democratic mayor of the city, 1927-1931. Mayoralty files; papers, 1922-1926, concerning the Ann Arbor Board of Education; also papers, 1922-1952, of Staebler and Son, automobile dealership.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Neil Staebler (donor no. 2417 ) and came to the library in 1948.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edward W. Staebler was an Ann Arbor businessman who managed an early automobile dealership. From 1927 to 1931, he served as Democratic mayor of the city.
The Edward W. Staebler papers consists primarily of correspondence and subject files from the period when he was mayor of Ann Arbor. Smaller portions of the papers concern the family automobile dealership, Staebler and Son, and his involvement with the Ann Arbor Board of Education.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Board of Education.; Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Depressions--1929--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Staebler, Edward William, 1872-1946.; Staebler and Sons (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Automobiles--1901-1910.; Children.; Staebler, Edward William, 1872-1946.; Staebler family.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Mayoralty Files 1927-1931
  - Correspondence
    - April-September 1927 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1927 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1928 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1928 (Box 1)
    - July-September 1928 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1928 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1929 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1929 (Box 1)
    - July-September 1929 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1929 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1930 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1930 (Box 1)
    - July-August 1930 (Box 1)
    - September-December 1930 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1931 (Box 1)
  - Topical File 1927-1932
    - Accountant and Accounting System (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Municipal Airport (Box 1)
    - Air Tour 1930 (Box 1)
    - Amateur Cinema (Box 1)
    - Amendments (proposed state) (Box 1)
    - Amendment of city charter re. pensions (Box 1)
    - Appointments to office (Box 1)
    - Aviation (Box 1)
    - Board of Public Works 1927 (Box 1)
    - Board of Public Works 1929 (Box 1)
    - Board of Supervisors (Box 2)
    - Budgets (Box 2)
    - Building Code (Box 2)
    - Bus Service (Box 2)
    - City attorney (Box 2)
    - Clean Up-Paint Up Week (Box 2)
    - Complaints and Claims against the city (Box 2)
    - Council (communications to) (Box 2)
    - Day nursery reports (Box 2)
    - Election registration 1928 (Box 2)
    - Election of 1932 (Box 2)
    - Electrical inspection (Box 2)
    - Family Welfare Bureau (Box 2)
    - Financial statements of Ann Arbor (Box 2)
    - Finances and bonds (Box 2)
    - Fire department (Box 2)
    - Gasoline ordinance (Box 2)
    - Health unit, Washtenaw County (Box 2)
    - Highways (Box 2)
    - Hospital (proposed state psychopathic) (Box 2)
    - Hotels (Box 2)
    - Housing Law (Box 2)
    - Insurance of city property (Box 2)
    - Keihl, Frank (dismissal) (Box 2)
    - Labor Unions (Box 2)
    - League of Michigan Municipalities (Box 2)
    - Market Committee (Box 2)
    - Market site (Box 2)
    - Messages and recommendations (Box 2)
    - Michigan Central Railroad (Box 2)
    - Newkirk, H. Wirt (Box 2)
    - Ordinances (Box 2)
    - Park Commission (Box 2)
    - Permits issued (Box 2)
    - Planning and Zoning Conference (Box 2)
    - Precincts [new] 1929 (Box 2)
    - Proclamations (Box 2)
    - Prohibition (Box 2)
    - Public and Community Service Committee (Box 2)
    - Real Estate Board (Box 2)
    - Salvation Army (Box 2)
    - Scrip and Tax anticipation notes (Box 2)
    - Sewage disposal system (Box 2)
    - Sewer construction (Box 3)
    - Soliciting (law on) (Box 3)
    - Speeches and material for talks (Box 3)
    - Supervisor's investigation of road commission (Box 3)
    - Taxation, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Taxis, regulations (Box 3)
    - Treasurer's reports (Box 3)
    - Unemployment, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan (Box 3)
    - University of Michigan Fraternity Raid 1931 (Box 3)
    - Veterans bonus (Box 3)
    - Voting machines (Box 3)
    - Washington Bicentennial Program (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw Museum (Box 3)
    - Water Department, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Y.M.C.A. (Box 4)
    - Youth Commission (Box 4)
    - Zoning (Box 4)
- Other activities
  - Ann Arbor Board of Education 1922-1926, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Staebler and Son automobile dealership 1922-1952
    - American Road Builders Association (Box 4)
    - Bankruptcy court (Box 4)
    - Bookkeeper applications (Box 4)
    - Coal cubing machine (Box 4)
    - Credit ratings (Box 4)
    - Dixie Refining Company (Box 4)
    - Gas heating (Box 4)
    - Gasoline tax (Box 4)
    - Salaries and wages (Box 4)
    - United Reproducers Corporation (Box 4)
    - Miscellanea (Box 4)
    - Financial statements 1931-1952, 1 folders (Box 4)
  - Order of the Eastern Star 1932-1944 (Box 4)
  - Rotary International Service Committee 1937-1940 (Box 4)
- Photographs, 1870-1906
  - Portraits, presumably of Staebler family members; and copy print photographs of Staebler and others driving automobiles sold by Staebler, 2 envelopes (Box 4)